Dear fellow practitioners, today
Kính thưa các quý đạo hữu, hôm nay chúng
we have accomplished a
ta đã làm được một cái hạnh công đức rất
very good deed: we have made an offering to the
là tốt đẹp, đó là chúng ta được đi cúng
monastic retreat on behalf of
dường trường hạ thay cho toàn thể câu
our entire Golden Club.  This is a
lạc bộ quốc vàng của chúng ta. Đây là
Buddhist secondary school, so the
trường trung cấp Phật học thì nơi mà các
monks also study here, not just spend their time in
quý thầy học nữa chứ không phải mỗi an
retreat.  We must understand
cư không. Chúng ta phải rõ biết một điều
that the venerable monks who have renounced worldly life and become monks are
là các quý thầy đã xả tục xuất gia là
those who have left home to practice for the benefit of all sentient beings
những người vì lợi ích của chúng sinh mà
.  That is something that
xuất gia tu tập. Cái điều đó là điều mà
we Buddhists, due to our attachment to the five desires, are
Phật tử chúng ta do tham đắm ngũ dục
unable to do.  We're only aiming
không làm được. Chúng ta mới là hướng
towards it; we can't actually do it yet.
tới thôi chứ chúng ta không làm được.
My dear friends, in this life and possibly in the
Thưa quý hữu trong kiếp này còn có thể
next, it is certainly possible to achieve this
là kiếp sau chắc chắn là có thể làm
.  Is that correct, fellow practitioners?  The
được. Có đúng không các quý đạo hữu? Thì
offerings made during the rainy season retreat
cúng dường trong mùa an cư kiếp hạ thì
have a very special merit:
nó có một cái công đức rất là đặc biệt
for three months, monks from
đó là các quý thầy trong 3 tháng là từ
all over the country can gather here.  That
khắp mọi nơi các thầy có thể dồn về. Đấy
means that during the three-month rainy season retreat, the
tức là trong 3 tháng ân cư kiết hạ các
monks gather together to practice according to the
thầy tập trung lại tu tập theo truyền
tradition of the Buddhas of the three ages.  The monastic community
thống của ba đời chư Phật. Tăng đoàn bao
always gathers together for practice, but
giờ cũng tập trung lại tu tập và tập
what is the purpose of this gathering?  It is precisely to cultivate the six harmonies, as
trung để làm gì? Chính là để tu lục hòa
you all understand, because the six harmonies are very
đấy các quý đã hiểu vì lục hòa là rất là
noble.
cao quý.
I might be able to say I'm not greedy or angry when I'm alone,
Một mình mình có thể mình bảo mình không
but when there are two or more people involved, greed and anger
tham không sân nhưng mà ở hai người trở
will arise.
lên thì nó sẽ tham nó sẽ sân. Thế cho
Therefore, without them, it is impossible to practice spiritual cultivation
nên là không có chúng thì không thể tu
.  That's right, fellow practitioner.  I need them to practice spiritual cultivation;
được. Đó quý đạo hiữu. Phải có chúng mới
don't think I can cultivate it alone
tu được chứ đừng ai nghĩ tôi tu một mình
.  I cannot practice self-cultivation.  Because when I'm alone, I
tu được. Tu mình không tu được. Vì một
don't have the environment for
mình mình không có môi trường để cho
my negative thoughts to
những cái bất thiện tâm của mình nó bật
surface.  If it doesn't pop out, we can't pull it
ra. Nó không bật ra chúng ta không nhổ
out.  It just lies dormant inside.  For
được đi. Nó cứ ngủ ngầm ở trong thôi. Ví
example, if I don't go in and wait for my favorite tea,
dụ như mình không vào đợi trà mình thích
I'll become a monk.  If I'm angry, I'll become a nun, otherwise I won't
thì mình đi tu. Mình dỗi mình đi tu mình
.  How then can we
không thì thôi. Thì ta làm sao ta biết
know our own spirit?  How can we know if
được ta tinh thần? Ta làm sao ta biết
our minds are aligned with one path: faith
được tâm ta nó vào một dòng là tín tâm
in the Buddha's teachings and diligent practice?
với Phật pháp, chăm chuyên tu tập. Tại
Because when we're at home, if we're upset, we practice meditation; if not,
vì chúng ta ở nhà thì dỗi thì tu, không
then so be it.  Then, Buddhist teachings
dỗi thì thôi. Thế thì Phật pháp chưa
are not yet important to us.  How
phải là quan trọng đối với chúng ta. Thế
then can we possibly do good
thì chúng ta làm sao mà hướng thiện
?  Whether a person is inclined towards goodness or
được? Con người ta ấ hướng thiện hay
not depends on their heart's unwavering love and devotion to the
không là chính ở cái tâm yêu quý không
Buddha's teachings. Only then will we know if we are inclined towards
rời Phật pháp thì mình biết mình hướng
goodness, my esteemed fellow practitioners.  Because Buddhist
thiện các quý đạo hữu ạ. Tại vì Phật
teachings are inherently virtuous,
pháp chính là thiện pháp mà các quý đại
do you understand, esteemed elders?  Buddhist teachings are essentially
hiểu không? Phật pháp chính là thiện
virtuous teachings.  If our hearts do not cherish and cherish the Dharma,
pháp. Nếu như tâm mình không yêu quý,
meaning they are not deeply committed to studying and practicing
tức là nó không đau đáu để tu học Phật
Buddhism, then we know that our hearts are not yet
pháp thì mình biết rằng tâm mình chưa
directed towards that path of goodness.  The mind observes, giving
hướng về cái chỗ thiện đó. Tâm chư quán
examples.  For example, my child has two
lấy ví dụ. Ví dụ như con mình nó có hai
friends, one good friend and one
người bạn, một người bạn thiện và một
bad friend.  But it rarely
người bạn bất thiện. Thế nhưng nó lại
remembers or thinks about
trả mấy khi nhớ nghĩ đến cái người bạn
this kind friend, so
thiện này để đi chơi với người bạn thiện
naturally, its heart must be less
này thì đương nhiên trong tâm nó phải ít
kind.  If, deep down, it enjoys spending time
thiện. Nếu trong tâm nó thích đi chơi
with a good friend, it shows that it and
với người bạn thiện thì chính tỏ nó với
this good friend have much to
người bạn thiện này có nhiều cái để trao
exchange and like each other, enjoy learning from
đổi với nhau và thích nhau, thích học
each other, and enjoy being together.  Isn't that right, fellow
nhau, thích cùng nhau. Đúng không các
practitioners?  Then, the Buddha's teachings are truly a
quý đạo hữu? Thì Phật pháp chính là
good friend.  Do you see
người bạn thiện. Các quý đạo hữu thấy
anything unwholesome in Buddhist teachings, fellow practitioners?
Phật pháp có điều gì bất thiện đâu? Phật
Buddhist teachings are a good friend.
pháp là người bạn thiện.
Therefore, if someone has not yet directed their mind
Cho nên nếu như những ai chưa hướng tâm
towards practicing Buddhism, they should know that they have
tới tu Phật pháp thì mình biết rằng mình
not yet directed their mind towards goodness.
chưa hướng tâm được đến điều thiện đâu.
Not yet dedicated to doing good,
Chưa chăm chuyên được về điều thiện,
not yet delighted in doing good.  And of course, in
chưa thích thú điều thiện. Và đương
many lifetimes, we can't be
nhiên như vậy nhiều kiếp mình không thể
sure we'll be happy.
chắc được mình sẽ hạnh phúc.
Those who have not diligently practiced
Nếu như những ai chưa chăm chuyên tu
Buddhist teachings will know that in many lifetimes they have experienced
Phật pháp thì biết rằng nhiều kiếp còn
more suffering than joy.  As for those who wholeheartedly
khổ nhiều hơn vui. Còn những ai trăm
practice Buddhism, who are devoted to the
chuyên tu Phật pháp, người ta hướng tới
Dharma, and diligently cultivate it,
Phật pháp, chăm trí tu Phật pháp thì
they know that in many future lives
người ta biết là nhiều kiếp về sau người
they will experience much joy and very little suffering.   Being
ta nhiều vui và rất ít khổ.
in the club has helped
Trong câu lạc bộ thì đã giúp cho chúng
us a lot, providing us with opportunities to practice and cultivate our skills
ta rất là nhiều những cái để chúng ta
.  That means
tạo điều kiện, chúng ta tu tập rồi. Tức
our minds are always focused.  When we need to take a break,
là tâm chúng ta lúc nào cũng hướng. Nghỉ
we ask permission first, and then we listen
thì chúng ta xin phép rồi chúng ta nghe
later, meaning we want to focus our minds on doing
sau tức là để cho làm sao tâm mình hướng
good.  I'm busy, but I'd like to take some time
thiện. Tôi có bận nhưng tôi xin phép
off.  I resumed my monastic life later.  Does that mean
nghỉ. Tôi lại tu lại sau. Thế có phải là
my heart is always yearning for
tâm mình lúc nào cũng đau đau hướng
goodness?   If a
thiện không?
person's heart is deeply inclined towards goodness, then
tâm đau đáu hướng thiện thì người đó
in this lifetime, their karma is very easily
ngay kiếp này các nghiệp rất dễ chuyển
transformed, and in many lifetimes, suffering will
hóa và nhiều kiếp thì khổ nó hầu như là
appear very rarely.  Because wherever the mind is directed, that's where the
rất ít xuất hiện. Bởi vì tâm hướng về
fruit will be.  When the mind is inclined towards
đâu thì quả nó về đấy. Tâm hướng về bất
evil, evil results.  A heart inclined towards
thiện thì quả bất thiện. Tâm hướng về
goodness will yield good results.  My dear fellow practitioners,
thiện thì quả thiện. Các quý đạo hữu ạ,
we often say that we don't practice spiritual cultivation, yet we
mình cứ nói rằng mình không tu mà mình
demand happiness.  No, there isn't.  Only virtuous actions
đòi hạnh phúc. Không có đâu. Thiện pháp
bring happiness.  When our hearts are filled with love and
mới mang lại hạnh phúc. Khi tâm mình yêu
goodness, all evil deeds are
miến đều thiện thì các ác nghiệp nó được
eradicated, my esteemed fellow practitioners.  Therefore,
tiêu trừ các quý đạo hữu ạ. Thế cho nên
diligence brings blessings
cái sự tinh tấn thì sinh ra phúc báo
.  Those who are diligent will transform their
đấy. Ai tinh tấn thì người đấy sẽ chuyển
karma.  Do you see that, my esteemed friends?
nghiệp. Đấy các quý đạo hữu thấy không?
If we have any karma, we will always be preoccupied with it
Nếu chúng ta có nghiệp gì chúng ta đau
.  If you practice meditation two, three, or four times a day for 49 days,
đáu luôn. 49 ngày ngày tu hai thời, ba
will you see a rapid transformation
thời, bốn thời có thấy nhanh chuyển
?  If our hearts are strongly inclined towards goodness,
không? Thế ta tâm ta hướng thiện một
then things will change quickly.
cách mạnh mẽ thì nó sẽ nhanh chuyển.
But what if today you're in prison, tomorrow you're off, the day after that you're not paying
Thế còn nếu mà hôm nay tù mai nghỉ ngày
attention at all, and you're being constantly harassed and having your
kia nghỉ chả để ý gì lại ban cắn sự gọi
throat sore before you even get to go to the gathering? How can you
gọi rát cả cổ mới đi tụ thế thì làm sao
talk about your profession then, right, my esteemed fellow
nói chuyện nghề có phải không các quý
practitioners?  Therefore, here, I want to
đạo hữu? Cho nên ở đây tâm chớ quán chia
share with you, dear fellow practitioners, that our minds are inclined towards
sẻ với các quý đạo hữu là tâm hướng
goodness. We must keep
thiện chúng ta làm sao chúng ta phải để
in our minds...
trong tâm của chúng ta này chúng ta tâm
our minds have many kinds of minds,
của chúng ta có nhiều lắm tâm nọ tâm kia
but ultimately, they are only two:
nhưng tựu chung lại nó chỉ có hai thôi
good and anything unwholesome. When
thiện và bất gì bất thiện đó thiện thì
we desire to learn the Buddha's teachings,
chúng ta ham muốn học Phật pháp là chúng
we will discover that our minds are inclined towards
ta sẽ phát hiện ra tâm chúng ta hướng
goodness. When our minds are inclined towards goodness, evil
thiện thì khi tâm hướng thiện thì ác
karma is eliminated, and
nghiệp tiêu trừ
blessings increase. That's what you should all do, dear practitioners.
Phước báo sinh trưởng đó quý đạo y nhá.
Therefore, during the rainy season retreat,
Thế thì mùa an cư kiết hạ của chư tăng
we monks go to make offerings so that we can further strengthen our
chúng ta đi cúng dường để chúng ta càng
connection with the Three Jewels, receive blessings from the
kết duyên với tam bảo, được phúc báo từ
Three Jewels, and have our virtuous hearts
tam bảo để thiện tâm của chúng ta nó
strengthened, dear fellow practitioners.  So
được mạnh mẽ các quý đạo hữu ạ. Thế thì
why is it that after this rainy season retreat, many of you,
tại sao mà có thể là sau một mùa ăn cư
dear fellow practitioners, have been diligently
này các quý đạo hữu chúng ta vừa tinh
practicing and cultivating merit, and
tấn tu tập vừa tô bồi phúc báo thì rất
after this rainy season
rất là nhiều các quý đạo hữu sau mùa tu
retreat, you experience
tập an cư kiết hạ là chúng ta có những
very positive changes in
cái chuyển biến rất là tích cực trong
your karma and the blessings you receive,
nghiệp lực đấy và phước quả chúng ta
transforming your
được hưởng và chuyển hóa cái sự việc đau
suffering? You benefit in this way, dear fellow
khổ đấy các quý đạo hữu lợi ích như vậy
practitioners, so I wish you all continued
nhá cho nên chúc các quý đạo hữu chúng
diligence.
tinh tấn
Yeah!
Yeah.